Guide to the Rice University Carey Croneis office records (Provost, Acting President, Chancellor), 1950-1972 UA 093
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Carey Croneis office records (Provost, Acting President, Chancellor)
1950-1972
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Croneis, Carey
UA 093
10.5 Linear Feet
These records reflect the business conducted in the offices of Rice University Provost, (Acting) President, and Chancellor during Dr. Croneis' tenure in those positions, 1954-1970. Materials include correspondence, reports, and newsclippings pertaining to a wide variety of university activities. Records are arranged alphabetically according to folder titles assigned in the respective offices from which they came.
Biographical Note
Dr. Carey Croneis was born in 1901 in Bucyrus, Ohio, and received his B.S. degree from Denison University in 1922, followed by an M.S. in Geology from the University of Kansas in 1923, and a Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1928. He was an instructor at Radcliffe and lecturer at Wellesley in 1927-1928; assistant and then full professor at the University of Chicago, 1928-1944; and a member of the National Defense Research Council, 1942-1944. He then served as President of Beloit College from 1944 until he came to Rice.
Dr. Carey Croneis came to Rice (then Institute) in 1954 as Provost, and also as Harry Carothers Wiess Professor of Geology, charged with designing and organizing a Department of Geology at Rice. He served as Provost until 1960 and at that time assumed the additional responsibilities of Acting President following Pres. William V. Houston's resignation due to ill health. He served in both capacities until the appointment of Kenneth Sanborn Pitzer as President in July 1961. In that year, Dr. Croneis was named Chancellor, and held that position until his retirement in 1970. Dr. Croneis was named Wiess Professor Emeritus of Geology and Chancellor Emeritus. He died in January 1972.
Scope and Contents
These records reflect the business conducted in the offices of Rice University Provost, (Acting) President, and Chancellor during Dr. Croneis' tenure in those positions, 1954-1970. Materials include correspondence, reports, and newsclippings pertaining to a wide variety of university activities. Records are arranged alphabetically according to folder titles assigned in the respective offices from which they came.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
Transfered in 1972 and 1978 from the Chancellor's Office.
Arrangement
Records are arranged in one alphabetical run according to folder titles assigned in the respective offices from which they came.
Related Material
See also Dr. Carey Croneis personal papers, MS 402.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges
Document Types
letters (correspondence); notes; reports
Subjects (Persons)
Pitzer, Kenneth S. (Kenneth Sanborn); Croneis, Carey; Croneis, Carey
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University. Office of the Provost; Rice University; Rice University. Office of the President; Rice University. Office of the Chancellor
- Series I: Files A - K
  - Admissions - Special cases, 1964-65 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Admissions - Special cases, 1965/66 - 1968/69 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Admissions - Special cases, 1969/70 - 1971/72 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alumni, 1963-72 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alumni - Complaints, 1963-69 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alumni - Matching gifts, 1966-69 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alumni - Sallyport, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alumni Assembly, 1962-67 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Alumni Association, 1961-62 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Alumni Association, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alumni Association, 1965-68 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alumni Association, 1968-70 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Alumni Association, 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Alumni Association Executive Board minutes, 1962-64 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Association Executive Board minutes, 1965-66 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Alumni Association Executive Board minutes, 1967-68 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Alumni Association Executive Board minutes, 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Alumni Association Executive Board minutes, 1969-70 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Alumni Association honorees, 1966-70 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Alumni Fund, 1962-70 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - American Assembly, 1961-70 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - American Association of University Women, 1960-61 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - (M. D.) Anderson Foundation, Feb. - Oct. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Anderson Hall, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Architectural Society, 1963-69 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Architecture, Aug. 1960 - May 1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Architecture - Accreditation, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Architecture - Accreditation, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Architecture - Chilean Project, 1964-66 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Architecture - Curriculum, 1963-66 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Architecture - Department, 1961-64 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Architecture - Department, 1964-65 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Architecture - Degree program proposal, 1970-71 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Architecture - Faculty and facilities, 1963-65 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Architecture - Faculty and facilities, 1969-71 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Architecture - M. A. degree, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Architecture - Ph. D. degree, 1968-71 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Architecture - Salary and status records, 1971-72 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Architecture School - General files, 1965-67 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Architecture School - General files, 1967-68 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Architecture School - General files, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Architecture School - General files, 1969-70 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Architecture School - General files, 1970-71 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Architecture School - N.A.A.B. evaluation report (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Architecture Selection Committee for Director, 1971-72 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Architecture Urban Design Program, 1969-71 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Athletics, 1960-63 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Awards, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Band, 1962-67 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Bequests, 1964-68 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Biology, Oct. 1960 - Aug. 1961 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Business Office, Sept. 1960 - April 1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - (Faculty) Candidates interviewed by Carey Croneis, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chemical Engineering, Aug. 1960 - Sept. 1961 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chemistry, Sept. 1960 - Nov. 1961 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Civil Engineering, Dec. 1960 - Nov. 1961 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Classics, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Cohen, George S., 1963-71 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Congratulatory messages (appointment as Chancellor), July - Sept. 1961 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Contemporary Arts Association, 1962-68 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Credit Union, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Dean of Engineering, 1960-61 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Discipline cases, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Economics, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Economics and Business Administration, Oct. 1960 - May 1961 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Education, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Edwards Foundation, Oct. 1960 - June 1962 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Electrical Engineering, Sept. 1960 - June 1961 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - English, Sept. 1960 - April 1961 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Exchange Students' Activities, July 1960 - Jan. 1962 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Faculty and staff applications, 1962-72 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Faculty leaves of absence, 1956-62 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Fondren Library, 1961-63 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Fondren Library, 1964-70 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Fondren Library - Branch library problem, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Fondren Library - Graduate research addition, 1965-69 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Fondren Library - R.I.C.E., 1963-70 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Food Committee, 1950-62 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Foreign Languages, Nov. 1960 - April 1961 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Foreign Scholars, 1958-63 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Forensic Society, Oct. 1961 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Freshman Orientation Program, 1961-62 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Geology, Oct. 1961 - April 1962 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Geology, June 1960 - April 1962 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Germanics, 1964-70 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Graduate Research Center (of the Southwest), 1961-69 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Graduate Studies, Sept. 1960 - April 1961 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Grants - Research, 1963-72 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Guerry, Alex Jr., 1966-68 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Gulf Coast Geoscience Center/Gulf Universities Research Corporation (G.U.R.C.), 1962-64 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - G.U.R.C. and Rice University, 1964-65 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Health and P. E., Sept. 1960 - June 1961 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - History, Nov. 1960 - June 1961 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Honor Council, Student Association, 1952-62 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Interim Report to the Board by Dr. Croneis, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Series II: Files L - Z
  - Latin American Programs, 1964-67 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Loewenheim, Francis, 1964-1970 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Masterson incident Board report, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Mathematics, Oct. 1960 - April 1961 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Mechanical Engineering, Aug. 1960 - March 1964 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Military Science, 1964-69 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Military Science/Army-Navy Day, 1965-71 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Military Science/Army R.O.T.C. 1962-71 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Military Science/Naval Science, 1962-66 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Military Science/Navy R.O.T.C., 1969-71 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Military Science/R.O.T.C., 1969-70 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Milligan, W. O. (Chemistry Department), Sept. 1960 - Sept. 1961 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, June 1960 - Jan. 1962 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - M.O.H.O.L.E., 1963-66 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Music, 1961-69 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Music, 1963-71 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - N.A.S.A., 1960-72 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, Sept. - Nov. 1960 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Philosophy, Nov. 1960 - May 1961 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Physics, Sept. 1960 - June 1961 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Pike, Bishop (James A.), 1960 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Pitzer, Kenneth S., May 1961 - March 1962 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - President Pitzer's resignations, 1968-70 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Presidential Selection Committee, 1968-70 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - President's Office: Correspondence, 1962-64 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - President's Office: Correspondence, 1963-68 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Psychology Department, Jan. - June 1961 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Rayzor, J. Newton (Board of Governors), March 1960 - April 1962 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Religious activities, 1967-71 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Rice Players, 1962-66 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Rice University Associates, 1945-62 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Rice University Pamphlet, 1960-62 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Scholarships A-B, 1964-71 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Scholarships C-G, 1963-71 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Scholarships H-P, 1963-70 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Scholarships R-T, 1962-69 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Scholarships U-Z, 1962-70 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Self-Study 1964 - budget (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Self-Study 1964 - Central Committee (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Self-Study 1964 - Central Committee special reports (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Self-Study 1964 - Dean's reports (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Self-Study 1964 - departmental reports (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Self-Study 1964 - Rice committees (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Self-Study 1964 - special areas (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Self-Study 1964 - standards (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Self-Study 1964 - Visiting Committee (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Semicentennial commemorations and awards, 1962-65 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Semicentennial Committee, 1960-64 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Semicentennial Committee, 1960-64 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Semicentennial Committee - delegates accepting, 1962-63 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Semicentennial Committee - delegates declining, 1961-62 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Semicentennial Committee - delegates suggested, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Semicentennial Committee - Inaugural, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Semicentennial Committee Minutes, 1960-62 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Semicentennial Convocation, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Semicentennial - Dedication of Rayzor Hall, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Semicentennial expenses, 1962-63 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Semicentennial film, 1962-63 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Semicentennial Historian, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Semicentennial Inaugural Dinner, 1961-62 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Semicentennial Inauguration of President Pitzer, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Semicentennial major meetings and events, 1961-63 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Semicentennial miscellaneous, 1961-66 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Semicentennial newspaper clippings, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Semicentennial President's Reception, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Semicentennial Symposia, 1962-63 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Semicentennial Symposia, 1962-63 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Society of Rice University Women, 1968-70 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Sociology, September 1960 - May 1961 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Southwest Athletic Conference, 1964-68 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Southwestern Assembly, 1958 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Southwestern Assembly, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Southwestern Assembly, 1961-64 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Southwestern Assembly, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Southwestern Assembly, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Southwestern Assembly, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Southwestern Assembly, 1964-67 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Southwestern Assembly, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Southwestern Assembly, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Southwestern Assembly, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Superior Oil Scholars, 1957-70 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Texas Women's University, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Tax (Reciprocal Exemption from Inheritance Tax-SB 29), 1962-63 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Tuition, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Tuition, Room Board, 1963-66 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Tuition Studies, 1962 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Universidad Autonoma de Guadalajara (U.A.G.) - Advisory Committee, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - U.A.G. - Conference on Relations Between Private Enterprise and the University, 1964 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - U.A.G. - Development Program, 1963-64 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - U.A.G. - Guadalajara/Rice University Project, 1962-71 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - U.A.G. - Guadalajara/Rice University Project (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - U.A.G. - Guadalajara/Rice University Project (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - U.A.G. - Guadalajara/Rice University Project (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - U.A.G. - Guadalajara/Rice University Project (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - U.A.G. - Guadalajara/Rice University Project (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - U.A.G. - Guadalajara/Rice University Project reports and photographs, 1963 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - U.A.G. - Miscellaneous, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Vandiver - Acting President, 1969-71 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Visiting Lecturers - General, 1964-68 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Visiting Lecturers - Eisenhower Convocation, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Visiting Lecturers - Johnson, Lyndon Baines, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Visiting Lecturers - Kennedy, President John F., 1962 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Visiting Lecturers - Kreisky, Dr. Bruno, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Visiting Lecturers - Peterson lecturer, 1965-66 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Visiting Lecturers - Thomas, Albert, 1963-66 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Visiting Lecturers - Weingarten, Joe, 1963-67 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - West Estate (Clear Lake), 1955-59 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - West Estate (Clear Lake), 1961-67, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 3)